<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V4.1.2.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/4.1.2.5/sdocbook.dtd">
<!-- $id$ --><article>
  <title><literal>ToscanaJ</literal> 1.0 System Installation and Setup Guide</title>

  <section>
    <title>Contents of the Distribution</title>

    <para>The <literal>ToscanaJ</literal> distribution consists of a single
    compressed file containing all the files needed to run <literal>ToscanaJ</literal>
    and the editor for <literal>ToscanaJ</literal>-files, <literal>Elba</literal>.
    The compressed file contains the following files and directories:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>licence.txt</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Contains the licencing information</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>readme.txt</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A short text file with similar information to this text</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>run-elba.bat</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A batch file to run <literal>Elba</literal> on Windows
          computers</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>run-elba.sh</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A shell script to run <literal>Elba</literal> on Unix
          computers</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>run-toscanaj.bat</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A batch file to run <literal>ToscanaJ</literal> on Windows
          computers</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>run-toscanaj.sh</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A shell file to run <literal>ToscanaJ</literal> on Unix
          computers</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>ToscanaJ.jar</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Java Archive file containing the programs themself</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>toscanaj.prop</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A Java properties file storing the configuration and the
          session management information of the programs. This file changes
          everytime one of the programs is closed</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>examples</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This directory contains two example data sets, one of them in
          two variations ­ the PCTest example exists in an English version,
          which uses the internal database engine and in a German version,
          which does not use the database</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>libs</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This directory includes all libraries needed to run
          <literal>ToscanaJ</literal> and <literal>Elba</literal>. Please
          refer to the text files in this directory to check the licencing
          information for the libraries</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Installing and Running <literal>ToscanaJ</literal></title>

    <para><literal>ToscanaJ</literal> runs on every Java 1.4 Standard Edition
    (SE) enabled platform. At the time of writing this includes Windows, Linux
    (x86) and a range of different Solaris versions. Other platforms have
    announced support for Java 1.4 SE, most noticably MacOS X. Please make
    sure your system supports Java 1.4 SE before installing
    <literal>ToscanaJ</literal>.</para>

    <para>Assuming Java is set up properly, <literal>ToscanaJ</literal> needs
    no special installation procedure, extracting the contents of the
    distribution into some read and write<footnote><para>Write access is
    required only onto the file toscanaj.prop</para></footnote> accessible
    location is sufficient. Afterwards <literal>ToscanaJ</literal> and
    <literal>Elba</literal> can be started using the appropriate batch or
    shell scripts for the platform, e.g. <command>run-toscanaj.bat</command>
    for running <literal>ToscanaJ</literal> on a Windows computer or
    <command>run-elba.sh</command> for running <literal>Elba</literal> on a
    Linux/Unix computer. In case your platform is not supported by the scripts
    but does run Java 1.4 SE, please let us know. You should still be able to
    run the programs by executing a commands to the ones in the scripts.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Configuration Options</title>

    <para><literal>ToscanaJ</literal> tries to reduce the user interface by
    not offering too many options to the standard user. Since the program is
    applicable in a wide range of domains, its desired behaviour can be quite
    different, though. This fact is accomodated by having a range of
    configuration options which are accessible by adding/changing parameters
    in the properties file toscanaj.prop. These options are described in the
    following sections.</para>

    <para>Capitalization is relevant, i.e. all names have to use exactly the
    same spelling. Colors are given as six hexadecimal digits in the same way
    as they are in an HTML file, although the leading hash symbol has to be
    escaped with a backslash (see example below). Boolean values are turned on
    by setting the value to &#34;1&#34;.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Diagram representation</title>

      <para>All options for the diagram representation start with the text
      <command>&#34;DiagramSchema-&#34;</command>, followed by one of the
      items given in the list below.</para>

      <para>An example for this is the following:</para>

      <programlisting>DiagramSchema-backgroundColor=\#000030</programlisting>

      <para>This line in the properties file will change the background color
      to a dark blue.</para>

      <para>Here are all possible changes to the diagram colors:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>backgroundColor (color value)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>sets the background color of the whole diagram</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>topColor (color value)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>sets the top color of the gradient, i.e. the color of the
            uppermost node in the normal display options</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>bottomColor (color value)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>sets the bottom color of the gradient, i.e. the color of a
            node with empty extent or contingent (depending on the display
            options)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>foregroundColor (color value)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>sets the color used for text and other foreground elements
            not otherwise specified</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>nestedDiagramNodeColor (color value)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>sets the color used for nodes containing diagrams in the
            nested views</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>circleColor (color value)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>sets the color of the outline of the nodes</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>lineColor (color value)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>sets the color of the connecting lines in the diagram</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>circleSelectionColor (color value)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>sets the color used for highlighting a selected node</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>circleFilterColor (color value)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>sets the color used for highlighting nodes above a selected
            node</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>circleIdealColor (color value)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>sets the color used for highlighting nodes below a selected
            node</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>fadeOutValue (value between 0.0 and 1.0)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>determines how much non-highlighted parts of the diagram are
            faded during highlighting. A value of zero means no fading, a
            value of one means only the highlighted parts stay visible (not
            recommended)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>selectionLineWidth (positive integer value)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>the width of a line in the selected part of a diagram</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>labelFontName (name of font available on the platform)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>determines the font family used in the labels. Besides the
            font families available on your platform (e.g. <command>&#34;Arial&#34;</command>)
            you can also use the standard names <command>&#34;Serif&#34;</command>,
            <command>&#34;Sans-Serif&#34;</command> and <command>&#34;Monospaced&#34;</command>
            to select a general font type</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>labelFontSize (positive number)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>sets the size of the font in the labels</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>notRealisedDiagramNodeColor (color value)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>if given, not realized nodes<footnote><para>these are the
            nodes which are in the diagram but not represented by the data in
            the database, typically represented as smaller nodes</para></footnote>
            use this color instead of a gradient color</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>Other options to change the display of the diagram are:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>margin (positive integer value)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>sets the number of pixels the diagram uses as margin towards
            the edges of the available screen area</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>notRealizedNodeSizeReductionFactor (value between 0.0 and 1.0)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>determines how much smaller not realized nodes are compared
            to the normal nodes.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>gradientType (&#34;extent&#34; or &#34;contingent&#34;)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>determines if the node colors are calculated based on the
            extent sizes of the concepts or the object contingent sizes</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>scaleNodeSize (&#34;contingent&#34;, &#34;extent&#34;
          or&#34;none&#34;)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>if set to <command>&#34;extent&#34;</command> or
            <command>&#34;contingent&#34;</command>, the size of the node will
            change relative to the extent or object contingent size of the
            concept represented</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>User Interface Options</title>

      <para>Some options can be used to change the features available in
      <literal>ToscanaJ</literal>&#39;s main window. These are (given with
      their full keys):</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>ToscanaJMainPanel-offerGradientOptions (boolean)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>if turned on, the view menu in <literal>ToscanaJ</literal>
            will contain two entries to change between the two gradient styles
            (extent, contingent)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>ToscanaJMainPanel-offerNodeSizeScalingOptions (boolean)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>if turned on, the view menu in <literal>ToscanaJ</literal>
            will contain three entries to change between the node size scaling
            options (extent, contingent, none)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Debug Options</title>

      <para>A last set of options can be used to understand what happens
      behind the scenes. These are not supposed to be used in normal
      <literal>ToscanaJ</literal> system, but included for completeness.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>DatabaseConnection-logger (text value)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>this turns logging on the database connection on. The value
            can be either a pointer to a writable file or &#34;-&#34; to log
            onto the standard text output stream. Every call to the database
            will be logged, including the SQL commands used and the time
            stamps before and after the call</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>NodeView-displayVectors (boolean)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>if turned on, the coordinates of each node will be displayed
            beside the circles</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>